Guide to the Records of the Brooklyn Council for Social Planning BCMS.0039
Brooklyn Collection
Records of the Brooklyn Council for Social Planning
1931-1958
1948-1957
Brooklyn Collection
Brooklyn Council for Social Planning
BCMS.0039
28 Linear Feet 67 boxes
Historical Note
The Brooklyn Council for Social Planning (BCSP), originally called the Brooklyn Social Planning Committee, was founded in 1933, by a group of prominent citizens, social workers, and representatives of civic organizations who saw a need for an organization to coordinate local social services, especially in the face of funding cuts during the Great Depression. BCSP promoted, guided, and evaluated the health and welfare of the people of Brooklyn, and offered leadership to all groups in the community working to improve, extend, and prevent duplication of social services. The Council had two types of members: social and health agencies engaged in meeting the needs of Brooklyn residents; and individuals interested in these causes. Members comprised all religions, ethnic, and racial groups in the borough. BCSP aimed to build a community in which citizens would be fully employed, and have adequate standards of living, housing, recreation and health services, educational opportunity, and social and economic security.
BCSP sought to accomplish these goals in the following ways: promoting greater effectiveness in attacking social problems by mobilizing groups toward common goals; guiding the development of social services by planning the expansion of current services as well as new services for the future; collecting and maintaining data concerning Brooklyn so that planning would have a sound factual basis; providing information to the public on the facilities available to meet all types of needs; increasing the usefulness of social and health agencies by helping to relate their services to the needs of the community; communicating the needs of Brooklynites to city-wide programs through BCSP's affiliation with the Welfare and Health Council of New York City; developing local neighborhood councils in cooperation with neighborhood organizations; and using research on specific localities to develop services for those areas. BCSP also served to bring social needs to the attention of grant-giving agencies such as The Greater New York Fund. The Council sought to keep the public informed through press releases, bulletins and reports to focus borough-wide attention on social needs and on the desirability of supporting the agencies and institutions which met those needs. Through its active programming, conferences, and professional training for social workers, BCSP kept the social welfare needs of the community in the public eye.
BCSP was funded primarily by the Welfare and Health Council of New York City, later called the Community Council of Greater New York. When this organization resolved to cut funding to borough councils, including BCSP, as of December 31, 1956, BCSP was unable to find other sources of funding, and was forced to close its doors.
Scope and Contents
This collection comprises the records of the BCSP from its founding in 1933 until its demise in 1957, and is organized in ten series, as received from BCSP. Records are much more extensive for the years 1948-57 than for the earlier years of operation. The collection provides a comprehensive description of existing and needed social welfare services in Brooklyn during the years covered, as well as efforts to extend and improve these services in the following areas: child care, adoption and foster care, juvenile delinquency, recreational facilities, neighborhood organization, medical and mental health services, the practice of social work, housing needs, discrimination and segregation issues, veterans services, and volunteerism. In some instances the policies are at odds with current practice (the general approval of public housing projects, for example); in others (the recognition of discrimination in the apportionment of services to certain minority neighborhoods, or school segregation), the records point to a growing cognizance of social injustices which would culminate in the civil rights movement of the 1960s.
Minutes of meetings present the most comprehensive picture of the administrative and program activities of BCSP during all years of operation, and also include minutes of a related organization, the Brooklyn Health Council. The administrative activities of the organization, including its finances and fund raising, Board of Directors, membership activities, and early history are chronicled in correspondence and related material in Series 2, administrative files. The program files, Series 3, demonstrate the organization's active approach in addressing the needs of all groups, and include committee correspondence, some minutes of meetings, press clippings, and related pamphlets and reports. Programs include annual meetings, family and child welfare activities, group work and recreation, health care services, housing, neighborhood organization, professional training, services to African-Americans, transportation, World War II veterans' services, volunteerism, and youth services.
The hierarchy of welfare and health councils in New York City during this period is evident in Series 4, which chronicles BCSP's relationship with other related organizations, including its parent organization, the Welfare and Health Council of New York City (later called the Community Council of Greater New York); its sister organizations in the other boroughs; and its distant relatives in other cities. BCSP's offspring, in the form of various Brooklyn neighborhood councils, are documented in Series 5, which also includes general information on many neighborhoods in the borough.
BCSP's interests and programs included issues involving city, state and local government agencies. Its work with and relationship to various municipal agencies is revealed in correspondence, press clippings, reports and publications in Series 6. Correspondence with and records of cooperative projects with nongovernment organizations and agencies, including Brooklyn College, Brooklyn Public Library, Greater New York Fund, and the Urban League of Greater New York, is found in Series 7, which also includes a large group of files on related nonprofit organizations, mostly in Brooklyn, whose purposes were in sympathy with those of BCSP.
Many BCSP projects were anticipated by extensive research and information about particular topics or issues. Publications, pamphlets, press clippings, reports, and other material covering the aged, juvenile delinquency, social welfare legislation, narcotics abuse and Puerto Rican communities in New York, and other issues can be found in Series 8, subject files.
As the culmination of a project, or as an impetus to social change, BCSP published reports and pamphlets on issues of concern; these are found in series 9. Series 10 contains scrapbooks assembled by BCSP to record the press coverage of its activities and on important issues of the day.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in 10 series as follows: 1. Minutes, 1933-57 2. Administrative files, 1933-58 [bulk 1945-57] 3. Program files, 1934-57 [bulk 1946-57] 4. Related welfare and health councils, 1932-57 [bulk 1946-57] 5. Brooklyn welfare and health councils, 1931-1957 6. Related government agencies, 1938-57 [bulk 1950-57] 7. Related non-government agencies, 1937-1957 [bulk 1945-57] 8. Subject files, 1933-1957 [bulk 1950-57] 9. BCSP publications, 1939-57 10. Press clipping scrapbooks, 1933-1957 [bulk 1933-1950]
The files are maintained as much as possible in the order in which they were received from BCSP, resulting in the occasional duplication of information between the various series. Folder titles were taken as much as possible from the original BCSP folders; some archaic terms were maintained. The researcher is advised to look for information on their topic in each series to receive the most comprehensive picture of the activities or services provided by BCSP in a particular geographic area or for a specific type of service.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The provenance of this collection is unknown but it is thought to have been deposited with the Brooklyn Public Library upon the demise of the organization in 1957.
Related Materials
Adamson, F. (1941) A study of the recreational facilities of the Brownsville section of Brooklyn. New York, NY.
BCSP (1940-1943). [Brooklyn neighborhood surveys]. Brooklyn, NY: the Council.
BCSP, (1949). Brooklyn recreation directory; prepared by the Brooklyn council for social planning in cooperation with School of home economics, Pratt institute. Brooklyn, NY: the Council.
BCSP (1950). Report of the Tompkins Park Youth Leadership Project. Brooklyn, NY: the Council.
BCSP (1951). Growing up in Brooklyn: a report of Brooklyn's Little White House Conference on Children and Youth. Brooklyn, NY: the Council.
BCSP (1953). Report on survey of Brooklyn agencies rendering services to Puerto Ricans. Brooklyn, NY: the Council.
BCSP (1954). All about Brooklyn: a handbook for Brooklynites. Brooklyn, NY: the Council.
Mintzer, J. (1940). Neighborhood study of the Park Slope community in Brooklyn; conducted under the auspices of the Brooklyn Council for Social Planning. New York, NY: New York School of Social Work.
BCSP (1950). Publicity guide for social agencies in Brooklyn. Brooklyn, NY: the Council.
BCSP (1953). New steps to mental health. Brooklyn, NY: the Council.
Brooklyn College; Community Council of Greater New York; Greater New York Fund; Urban League of Greater New York; White House Conference on Children and Youth (1951: Brooklyn, N.Y.)
- Minutes, 1933-1957
  - BCSP minutes, 1933-1957
    Arrangement
    Arranged in chronological groups as found in binders assembled by BCSP.
    Scope and Contents
    This subseries is comprised of the minutes of meetings of the Board of Directors and the various committees of the Brooklyn Council for Social Planning from its founding in 1933 until its demise in 1957. Administrative committees include Nominating, Executive, Finance, and Membership. The various programs of the BCSP are represented in their committee minutes (See also Series 3, Program files), as well as the following committees not represented in the program files: Committee on Unattached Men (homeless men), Population Changes, Neighborhood Development, Employment Problems of Older Women, and Food Stamps. During World War II, committee activities addressed war-related issues: Committee on War Activities; Japanese-American Committee, which assisted in the adjustment of "loyal" Japanese-Americans, and assisted Japanese coming to Brooklyn according to the plans of the War Relocation Authority.
    The minutes of the following committees were removed before this collection came to the Brooklyn Public Library: Puerto Rican Steering Committee meeting minutes, September 1952 - December 1957, were given to the Brooklyn Bureau of Social Service and Children's Aid Society, December 31, 1957.
    Mental Hygiene Committee, June 1933 - May 1956, were given to the Brooklyn Association for Mental Health, December 31, 1957. Minutes of the committee from September 1956 - December 1957 are included in this series.
    Health Careers Committee, January - April 1956, were given to the Brooklyn Tuberculosis and Health Association, December 31, 1957.
    - June 1933 – May 1939 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
    - July 1939 – June 1940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - July 1940 – June 1941 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
    - July 1941 – June 1942 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
    - July 1942 – June 1943 (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
    - July 1943 – June 1944 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - July 1944 – June 1945 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - July 1944 – June 1945 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - July 1945 – June 1946 (Box 3, Folder 2-4)
    - July 1946 – June 1947 (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
    - July 1946 – June 1947 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - July 1947 – June 1948 (Box 4, Folder 2-4)
    - July 1948 – June 1949 (Box 4, Folder 5-6)
    - July 1948 – June 1949 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - September 1949 – June 1950 (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
    - September 1950 – June 1951 (Box 5, Folder 4-5)
    - September 1951 – June 1952 (Box 5, Folder 6-7)
    - September 1952 – June 1953 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
    - July 1953 – June 1954 (Box 6, Folder 3-4)
    - July 1954 – July 1955 (Box 6, Folder 5-6)
    - July 1954 – July 1955 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - July 1955 – July 1956 (Box 7, Folder 2-4)
    - September 1956 – December 1957 (Box 7, Folder 5-6)
  - Brooklyn Health Council minutes, 1934-1944 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    The purpose of the Brooklyn Health Council was to bring together health agencies functioning in the community to coordinate and facilitate work, evaluate needs, initiate projects, and act as an information bureau. BCSP was a member of the Brooklyn Health Council, along with the City departments of Education, Health, Hospitals, Brooklyn Tuberculosis and Health Association, Visiting Nurse Association, and other agencies. These minutes were found with the BCSP minutes in separate binder.
- Administrative files, 1933-58 [bulk 1945-1957]; 1945-1957
  Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  The administrative files are comprised of a range of materials, including files on BCSP activities, Board of Director's correspondence, committee information, certificates of appreciation, finances and fund raising, founding, legal history, legislative policy, membership, personnel, and public relations.
  The Board of Directors files include general correspondence on issues relating to the administration of BCSP, and nominating committee correspondence regarding the appointment of Board members. There are significant letters to and from Brooklyn borough President John Cashmore, President Dwight D. Eisenhower, and the Brooklyn Daily Eagle, and an interesting chronicle of BCSP's involvement with Planned Parenthood Association.
  Committee files provide an understanding of the range of small committees essential to BCSP's overall mission. Finance files chronicle the budgetary history of the organization, and reveal the financial struggle BCSP underwent, eventually leading to its demise. The fund raising and finance committee files disclose important information on the fragile state of BCSP's finances during the "crisis campaign" of 1956-57, when BCSP sought alternative funding after learning that the Community Council of Greater New York, its major funder, would no longer provide financial support. History files describe BCSP's founding and mission, and include preliminary and revised bylaws. The diversity of activities and programs organized by BCSP are well documented in the press release files.
  - Activities of BCSP: Reports, 1939-1942 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Board of Directors: Correspondence: General, 1950-1952 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Board of Directors: Correspondence: General, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Board of Directors: Correspondence: General, 1954 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Board of Directors: Correspondence: General, 1955 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Board of Directors: Correspondence: General, 1956 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Board of Directors: Correspondence: Action Taken on Various Issues, 1954-1957 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Board of Directors: Nominating Committee: Correspondence, 1949-1951 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Board of Directors: Nominating Committee: Correspondence, 1953-1954 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Board of Directors: Nominating Committee: Correspondence, 1955-1956 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Board of Directors: Nominating Committee: Correspondence, 1957 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Board of Directors: Nominating Committee: Correspondence, 1939-1944 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Board of Directors: Nominating Committee: Correspondence, 1945-1948 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Certificates of Appreciation (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Committees: Committee on Committees (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Committees: Committee on the Formula for Greater NY Fund distribution: Correspondence, 1946-1951 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Committees: Executive Committee: Correspondence, minutes, 1946, 1955-1957 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Committees: Program Planning Committee and General Committee Structure (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Committees: Program and Structure Committee: Correspondence, 1956-1957 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Committees: Role of BCSP in Community Coordination: Report (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Committees: Ways and Means, 1956 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Committees: Youth Conference Committee, 1946-1947 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Finances: Bank Account: National City Bank, 1956-1957 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Finances: Bank Account: Williamsburg Savings Bank: Regular account, 1955-1957 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Finances: Bank Account: Williamsburg Savings Bank: Campaign funds, 1957 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Finances: Budgets, 1953-1956 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Finance Committee: Correspondence and Minutes, internal and external (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Finances: Expenses, 1947-1952 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Finances: Expenses, 1952 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Finances: Expenses, 1953-1955 (Cumulative Statements) and 1953-1956 (Monthly Statements) (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Finances: Fund distribution to recreation agencies, 1941-1943 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Finances: Fundraising, General: Sample solicitation letters (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Finances: Fundraising: Correspondence with individuals, 1941-1947 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Finances: Fundraising: Special committee of seven, 1946 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Finances: Fundraising: Luncheon, 1950 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Finances: Fundraising: Correspondence with outside organizations, 1948-1954 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Finances: Fundraising: Contributions and correspondence acknowledging contributions, 1952-1954 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Finances: Fundraising: Crisis Campaign, 1956-1957 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Finances: Fundraising: Finance Crisis: Internal correspondence, 1956-1957 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Finances: Fundraising: Financial Crisis: External correspondence, 1956-1957 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Finances: Fundraising: Crisis Campaign Committee, 1956-1957 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Finances: Fundraising: Crisis Campaign: Promotional material, 1956-1957 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Finances: Fundraising: Crisis Campaign: Press conference, 1956-1957 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Finances: Fundraising: Crisis Campaign: Letters to donors to emergency fund, 1956-1957 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Finances: Fundraising: Crisis Campaign: Letters to Brooklyn agencies, 1956-1957 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Finances: Fundraising: Crisis Campaign: Letters to former member organizations, 1956-1957 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Finances: Fundraising: Crisis Campaign: Responses from former individual members and contributors, 1956-1957 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Finances: Fundraising: Crisis Campaign: Responses from former local organization members, 1956-1957 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Finances: Fundraising: Crisis Campaign: Responses from foundations, 1956-1957 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Finances: Fundraising: Crisis Campaign: Responses from non-member organizations, 1956-1957 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Finances: Fundraising: Greater New York Fund, 1957 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Finances: Treasurer's report, 1951-1956 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - History: Dissolution of BCSP: Correspondence, 1958 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - History: Founding of BCSP: Organizational meetings, 1933-1934 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Legal: By-laws, 1937-1948 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Legal: By-laws: Revision, 1955-1956 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Legal: Certificate of Incorporation, 1939 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Legal: Certificate of Report of Existence, 1951 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Legal: Consent forms for use of board members' names in fundraising (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Legal: Exemption from Federal Income Tax: Correspondence and rulings (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - Legal: Exemption from New York City Sales Tax (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - Legal: New York State Joint Legislature Committee on Charitable and Philanthropic Agencies survey, 1953 (Box 11, Folder 22)
  - Legal: Office Leases, 1949-1957 (Box 11, Folder 23)
  - Legislative Policy (Box 11, Folder 24)
  - Membership: Lists of member organizations, 1949-1955 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Membership: Committee correspondence, 1949-1955 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Membership: Membership solicitations, 1954-1955 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Personnel: Job descriptions, 1957 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Personnel: Personnel Committee and Personnel Practices Committee: Correspondence (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Personnel: Social Security Employer I.D. (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Personnel: Marion Lounsbury Foster, retirement reception, 19 September 1957 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Public Relations: Committee on Interpretation of Services (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Public Relations: Press releases, 1933-1944 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Public Relations: Press releases, 1945 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Public Relations: Press releases, 1946-1947 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Public Relations: Press releases, 1948-1950 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Public Relations: Press releases, 1951-1952 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Public Relations: Press releases, 1954-1957 (Box 12, Folder 14)
- Program files, 1934-1957 [bulk 1946-1957]; 1946-1957
  The BCSP program files contain the most complete description of the organization's activities in its various program areas.
  All sub-series are arranged alphabetically by topic with correspondence arranged chronologically.
  - General activities, 1937-1957
    Correspondence, minutes, and reports of annual meetings, lectures, forums and conferences sponsored by BCSP, and correspondence of committees charged with program activities (Program Committee, Needs and Resources Committee, and Plan and Scope Committee), are found in these files.
    - Annual Meeting, 1937 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Annual Meeting, 1938 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Annual Meeting, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Annual Meeting, 1940 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Annual Meeting, 1942 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Annual Meeting, 1943 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Annual Meeting, 1945 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Annual Meeting, 1941 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Annual Meeting, 1946 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Annual Meeting, 1947 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Annual Meeting, 1948 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Annual Meeting, 1949 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Annual Meeting, 1950 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Annual Meeting, 1952 (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Annual Meeting, 1953 (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - Annual Meeting, 1954 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Annual Meeting, 1955 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Annual Meeting, 1956 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Annual Meeting, 1957 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Combined Operations News Bulletin (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Committee on Needs and Resources Correspondence, 1934-1945 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Forums Conducted by BCSP, 1936-1937 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Plan and Scope Committee Correspondence, 1949-1950 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Program Committee Reports, 1941-1944 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Family and child welfare, 1946-1957
    Adoption, foster care, day care, and child welfare issues are well-documented in these files of committee and general correspondence, press clippings, and related material. Among the more interesting material is documentation of Brooklyn Day Care Week, and of the Little White House Conference on Children and Youth, an important event organized by BCSP in 1951 to address the social welfare needs of children in Brooklyn; this was a local follow-up to a national conference at the White House in Washington.
    - Child Care: Adoption Advertisements, Brooklyn Eagle, Correspondence (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Child Care Committee Correspondence, 1953-1954 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Child Care General Correspondence, 1948-1953 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Committee on the relationship between the Department of Welfare and other community organizations: correspondence, 1954-1956 (Box 15, Folder 4)